Yuri Balasanov, Ph. D.

2238 Asbury Ave., Evanston, Illinois 60201 (847) 644-9346

ybalasan@uchicago.edu; yuri.balasanov@earthlink.net

Education

1982 Ph.D., Probability Theory and Mathematical Statistics, Moscow State University, Russia.

1977 B.Sc., MS., Applied Mathematics, Moscow State University, Russia.

Qualifications summary

<u>Leader of multi-strategy businesses</u>. 1 year experience in building and running multi-strategy products.

Quantitative trader. 5 years of quantitative trading strategies development and trading.

<u>Researcher.</u> 28 years of creative applied mathematical and statistical research. 16 years in Financial Industry. <u>Professional research manager and team leader.</u> 25 years of effective management of research projects, teams and consulting companies.

Experienced university professor. 25 years of teaching experience (Moscow St. Univ., Univ. of Chicago).

Experience

Experience	
1991 – Present	Research Software International, Inc., Albany, New York.
	Founder and President (10 employees). Manage quantitative projects for financial industry.
	Founded and manage consulting team with an outstanding record of successfully
	completed
	research projects for leading companies of the industry.
1997 – Present	The University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois.
	Teach Fixed Income course within Program on Financial Mathematics.
May 2006	Lotsoff Capital Management, Chicago, Illinois.
– May 2007	Chief Investment Officer, Director of Fixed Income, Senior portfolio Manager. Led
	development of the <u>multi-strategy mutual fund and multi-strategy hedge fund</u> .
2001 - 2005	Ritchie Capital Management, Chicago, Illinois.
	<u>Director of Quantitative Research, Quantitative Trader.</u> Led development of analytical
	models (3) and trading strategies (2) of the company. Ran quantitative trading desk, traded
	some of the <u>trading strategies</u> (2) based on our models.
1993 - 2001	Bank of America, Chicago, Illinois.
	Senior Financial Engineer, Principal. Managed research group. Initiated projects, did
	market research, derivation and calibration of <u>major proprietary models for Global</u>
	Derivative Products Group at Bank of America (4).
	Developed <u>quantitative strategies and trading ideas</u> (5) for Global Interest Rates.
1987 – 1991,	Soviet-American Joint Venture DIALOGUE, Moscow, Russia.
	Leading Researcher, Project Manager. Statistical software development and marketing.
1982 - 1993	Moscow State University, Moscow, Russia.
	Professor, Senior Researcher. Taught Probability Theory, Mathematical and Applied
	Statistics, Financial Mathematics. Managed applied research projects

Personal skills

Excerpts from my professional reviews of the last 10 years (5)

Publications and References

Available upon request.

- (1) <u>Responsibilities at Lotsoff Capital Management:</u> Led the process of building the business platform (analytics, risk management system, asset allocation model, performance reporting), selecting strategies that fit together, adding new types of trades.
- (2) <u>Trading ideas and strategies developed and traded at Ritchie Capital Management:</u> Eurodollar futures and options, interest rates swaps and swaptions (USD and EUR curves), gold and crude oil vs. FX rates, FX volatilities, crude oil and natural gas futures, long-short portfolio of BKX index (banking industry index), SP index volatility.
- (3) <u>Businesses supported by the QR group at Ritchie Capital Management:</u> Firm wide Risk Management, Fixed Income, Global Relative Value, Energy, Credit Derivatives, Commodities Derivatives Trading, Convertible Bonds, Long Short. All developed models implemented by the group in C++ library of analytics with interfaces to the company systems and Excel spreadsheets.
- (4) <u>Major proprietary models for Global Derivative Products Group (Bank of America):</u> Multifactor interest rates model, volatility skew model, credit derivatives model, model for trading long vanilla FX options, model for proactive risk management of interest rates instruments.
- (5) <u>Quantitative strategies and trading ideas for the Global Interest Rates group (Bank of America):</u> Bond futures, bond bases, bond futures options, Eurodollar futures and options.
- (6) Excerpts from my professional reviews of the last 10 years: outstanding creative mind and great person to work with; excellent manager of research; innovative thinker, does not confine thinking to what has been tried in the mainstream; always a fresh perspective; very good in generating new projects and fresh, unorthodox ideas; always sees BIG picture; can effectively explain and sell his ideas to different people; always listens to others; great instinct for anticipating the "new thing" in financial engineering; dependable team player; strong leader; reliable when work under pressure; great teacher.

Meyer-Briggs type indicator ENTJ (Extraverted Thinking with Intuition) which in general means: logical, organized, structured, objective and decisive about what they view as conceptually valid; they enjoy working with others, especially when they can take charge and add a strategic plan; develop well-thought-out plans, provide structure to the organization, design strategies that work toward broad goals, take charge quickly and do what it takes, deal directly with problems caused by confusion and inefficiency; initiate an action oriented, energetic approach, manage directly and are tough when necessary, enjoy complex problems and are resourceful in managing them, run as much of the organization as possible. Preferred work environments: contain results-oriented, independent, and competent people focused on solving complex problems, are goal-oriented, have efficient systems and people, offer structure and focus on use of a master plan. Preferred learning style: cutting edge and theoretically based, delivered by experts, open to challenges and questions.